A Guide to the Papers of the Kean Family
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
full discussion on Senator [John James ?] Ingall's speech on the race question in which he proposes "justice -i.e., a full and fair vote"; Kean proposes the allotment of several states or portions of states solely to African American citizens (Jan 26 & Feb 10)
appointment of R.G.H. Keanto the University of Virginia Board of Visitors; Lizzie finally able to join Lancelot Keanin Sioux Cityafter two and a half years (Jan 29)
mentions the building up of cities such as Roanokeand Buena Vista(Mar 16)
mentions concerns of the University of Virginia Board of Visitors, especially the Law Department (Mar 18, Jul 20, Aug 10)
memorial observed for Robert E. Leeat the University of Virginia(Jun 8)
discussion of geology and J. Randolph Kean's trip to Wyomingwith the Princetongeology team (Aug 24)
the good reputation of the University of Virginia(Sep 9)
death of a V.M.I.Cadet Taliaferro of Norfolk by fist fighting with a Texas Cadet (Sep 28)
concern over possible Sioux Indian conflicts, J. Randolph Keanat Pine Ridge Agency, South Dakota, 9th Cavalry Battalion where the Indians were roused by Messianic promises and the Ghost Dance, events leading up to the massacre at Wounded Knee, South Dakota(1890 Nov 23 & 27; Dec 5; 1891 Jan 1)
disapproval of Benjamin Harrison's treatment of the Indian rebellion and quotes Texan [Louis Tresvant ?] Wigfall's disparaging comments concerning Jefferson Davis(Dec 5)
refers to the death of Sitting Bullleading to new hostilities; heavy snows at Roanokeand Fincastle(Dec 18)
1891
news that J. Randolph Keanis supposed to come East with the "K" troop detail; he spends June in Lynchburg(May 19)
J. Randolph Kean's gunshot accident & injury to his leg (Jul 30, Aug 3, 8, & 13; Oct 4, Nov 5)
J. Randolph Kean's pedigree for Sons of the American Revolution(Aug 18)
description of church run schools in Bedford City(Sep 14)
1892
new post assignment for J. Randolph Keanat St. Francis Barracks, St. Augustine, Florida(Mar 25)
legal problems at Edgehill following the death of Sarah [Randolph?]and the possible sale of the Thomas Jefferson manuscripts to Congress (Apr 30)
the University of Virginia- Johns Hopkins baseball game (May 21)
possible law partnership with Lile (May 26)
discussion of the possibility and theory of flight (Jun 11)
collapse of the old Winston furniture store on Main Street killing J.H.C. Winston and two black laborers (Jul 3)
higher education for women and the University of Virginia (Jul 21)
discussion of Sir J. Crichton Brown on Sex in Education (Aug 12)
the illness of Professor William Elisha Petersat the University of Virginia and the need of an assistant in Latin (Aug 20)
concern over cholera and the sewer system in Lynchburg(Sep 23)
J. Randolph Keanat Asheville, North Carolina(Oct 2)
J. Randolph Keanat Sioux City, Iowaon a visit (Oct 10)
Virginia politics, mention of the Dalton Gang and Coffeyville near where Pattie lives (Oct 15)
University of Virginia Board of Visitorsmeeting about the water supply (Oct 24)
more discussion of Virginiapolitics, death of R.G.H. Kean's sister Hattie (Nov 12)
details about the possibility of an endowed chair in English Literature at the University of Virginia(Dec 11,16, & 23)
1893
causes for personal depression (Jan 20)
more discussion about the endowed chair in English Literature at the University of Virginiaby Mrs. Kent (Jan 12)
the politics of Jefferson Coolidge(Feb 5)
opinions about child rearing (Feb 14)
Prescott Keanenlists in the Navy (Mar 21, Apr 4 & 18, Jun 2, Dec 1 & 23)
domestic adultery scandal in Nelson Countyinvolving two law partners (May 28)
University of Virginia Board of Visitorsmeeting re the Law Department and John B. Minor, Jr.(Jul 18 & 23)
"currency famine" [the Panic of 1893] and the suit against Congressman W.C.P. Breckinridgeof Kentuckyfor breach of promise to marry (Aug 13 & 20, Sep 5; see also 1894 Apr 15)
his opinion of Charles Triplett O'Ferrallas a candidate for Governor (Aug 20)
mentions Lucy Cocke(Aug 26)
sudden death of Dr. William B. Towles, Chair of Anatomy, and need for University of Virginia Board of Visitorsmeeting (Sep 17 & 21)
the engagement of J. Randolph Keanto Louise H. Young(1877-1915) (Sep 21)
R.G.H. Kean's gladness that his term on the Board of Visitorswill soon be over, "wild horses could not drag me into another term on the Board. Eight years of careful conscientious work, to the loss of much valuable time, in a most thankless duty, is as much as comes to my share." (Oct 13)
belief that Senator Daniel's speeches help keep Democrats from defecting to the 3rd party [the Populist Party ?], wish that Congress had stayed in session long enough to pass the Tariff and Election Bills rather than to go home to "look after their fences" (Nov 4)
wheat harvesting in Kansas(Dec 1)
the proposal to build a hospital at the University of Virginiapresented to the Board of Visitors (Dec 18)
the death of Dr. Morris, father-in-law of Pattie (Dec 23)
wife and child beating case in Lynchburg(Dec 23)
1894
University of Virginia Board of Visitorsmeeting about using the Fayerweather money to build and equip a hospital on grounds provided the Legislature adopts the hospital as a state hospital (Jan 13)
the death and observations about the life of General Jubal A. Early(Mar 4)
meeting Mr. George Young, father of Louise (Mar 9)
death of Aunt Betty [ Elizabeth Garlick Hill] (Mar 12)
discussion about the Census of 1890 and his fears about immigration, mention of a bullet proof "jacket," the Kelly Army at Omaha and Council Bluffs, and Populist agitators (Apr 29)
R.G.H. Kean's visit to St. AugustineJuly 7-August 3 (Jul 3 & 7)
death of Dr. W. C. Dabneyat the University of Virginia(Aug 21, Sep 6)
marriage of J. Randolph Keanon October 10 (Oct 10)
abuse of cocaine (Nov 5)
Eleanor going to Baltimoreto take lessons in design at one of the Art Schools (Nov 24)
the promotion of athletics at the University of Virginiaby the Board of Visitors (Nov 27)
Fayerweather will and the University of Virginia(Dec 26)
1895
visit from Lancelot Keanwhile on business in Washingtonlobbying for the railroads (Jan 13)
despair over understanding the "currency question" and the silver issue (Feb 13)
embezzlement case in Lynchburgby a teller of the First National Bank(Feb 24)
an assault against some lawyers in the Law Building (Feb 27)
the Spanish-Cuban trouble and his concern over possible U.S. involvement (Mar 24, Apr 10, May 5, Jul 28, and Sep 24)
description by Pat of a sandstorm which swept over the states to the east of the Rockies (Apr 10)
the University of Virginia's attempt to keep track of alumni, the retirement of Schele de Vere, and other news about the University (Apr 21)
the presentation of a bust of cousin John at the University of Virginia with a speech by Senator Daniel (Jun 7)
a copy of R.G.H. Kean's remarks about the Jubilee of Professor John B. Minorat the University of Virginia Law School from the Virginia Law Register (Jul 1)
Kean lost his position as City Attorney to A. W. Nowlin as a result of politics (Jul 6)
the death of cousin John [Barbee Minor?]and his burial at the University of Virginia cemeteryand the work of the Board of Visitors to fill Minor's chair (Aug 4)
Martha Jefferson Keanborn to J. Randolph Keanand Louise Kean(Sep 1)
Lancelot Keanrunning as a Democrat for State Senate in Iowa(Sep 24)
Prescott Keanon leave (Oct 7)
the Monroe Doctrine and the Cuban controversy; and Thomas Jefferson's role in the Monroe Doctrine (Oct 20, Dec 12)
Great Britain-Venezuela boundary dispute over Guiana (Oct 20, Dec 24)
"the disastrous fire" at the University of Virginia and rebuilding plans for the Rotunda(Nov 3, 10, Dec 2, 17)
Addie Kean's attendance at a meeting of the Daughters of the Confederacyin Atlanta(Nov 15)
Kean's opposition to a third term for President Grover Cleveland and Lancelot's lost election (Nov 22, Dec 4, and 1896 Apr 11)
1896
Great Britain- Venezuela controversy, national politics, and a discussion of the book The English in the West Indies (Jan 1, Apr 11)
South Africa and Great Britain-the failed raid led by [Dr. Leander Stan Jameson] into the Transvaal (Jan 8)
treaty between Russia and Turkey(Jan 27)
Cuba(Feb 4 & 29, Mar 21, Apr 11, May 4 & 10, Jun 2, 10, & 26, Oct 31, Dec 13, 19 & 20)
meeting of the Fortnightly Literary Club(Feb 15)
national politics (Feb 23)
the annual banquet of the University of VirginiaAlumni (Apr 19)
appointment of Fitzhugh Leeas Consul General, 1896-1898, to Havana, Cuba(Apr 19 & 24, Jun 2)
the misuse of Thomas Jeffersonquotes and discussion about the graduated income tax (May 10)
the chances of William McKinleybeing nominated at the Republican Convention and the silver controversy (Jun 10)
the Board of Visitors at the University of Virginia"unloading some of their deadwood" [professors] and the competition between the University and Washington & Lee Law Departments (Jun 20)
the platform of the Democratic Convention held in July in Chicago (Jun 26, Jul 12)
Kean's bad memories of the Republican Party during Reconstruction and his decision to vote for William Jennings Bryan(Jul 19)
the silver question (Jul 30)
discussion of economics and the disparity of the very rich and others (Aug 6)
death of Aunt Ellen [Wayles Harrison](Aug 16, 18)
the restoration of the Rotunda(Aug 18)
the Presidential race (Sep 19; Nov 14)
1897
the awkwardness of the Monroe Doctrine in a shrinking world; concern over the amount of the Federal budget pensions consume; and a discussion of Quo Vadis (Jan 5)
discussion of articles by Richard Harding Davis and sketches by Frederic Remington; problems of unemployment due to labor saving machinery and cheap immigrant labor (Jan 9 & 13)
Cuba(Feb 27, Mar 10)
distrust of Senator Daniel on the issues (Feb 27)
mentions various strikes and Eugene Debs(Aug 14)
discussion about Vaughan and other genealogy; New York politics (Oct 8, 23; Nov 6)
Buffalo Bill's Rough Riders (Oct 17)
activities of Addie Keanat the United Daughters of the Confederacy(Oct 23)
the death of a Georgiafootball player during a game at the University of Virginia(Nov 13, 21)
Dr. Randolph resigned the rectorship but not his membership on the Board of Visitors at the University of Virginiadue to poor health (Dec 13)
U.S. currency controversy; the problem of numerous pensioners and abuse of the pension system (Dec 19 & 25)
1898
genealogy (Jan 23)
article about pension abuse by Kean, "Pensions v. Coast Defenses" (Jan 17 & 23)
unsuccessful search for a servant willing to go to Bostonby Addie (Jan-Feb)
the Maine disaster and danger of war; the value of the Hawaiian Islands(Feb 19, 23,27; Mar 3, 9, 19, 27, 31; Apr 9, 14, 16)
Kean's serious illness (Apr 23, 28, 30)
There is also one folder of letters between Mrs. R.G.H. Kean, ( Adelaide Navarro de Maret Prescott) and Dr. J. Randolph Kean, from the time J. Randolph Keanwas teaching school in Onancock, Virginiain 1880 until 1922. There are also occasional letters from Addie to Randolph in the letters from R.G.H. Keanto his son described above.
There are four folders of letters from Dr. J. Randolph Keanto his wife, Louise Hurlburt Young Kean(1877-1915), beginning in 1898 after the declaration of war on Spainand continuing during his absences until shortly before her death in 1915. The first group of letters, in 1898, were written from Ft. Ethan Allen, Essex Junction, Vermont; Lynchburg, Virginia, where J. Randolph Keanattended his father in his last illness, May 16-June 13; and describing his life and work at Camp Cuba Libre, Jacksonville, Florida, Headquarters and Field Hospital, 2nd Division, 7th Army Corps, June 27-September 5, 1898. For more details of this period, 1898-1900, see his diary, volume number 4. The letters in 1900 were written while J. Randolph Keanwas stationed in Quemados, Cuba, the Headquarters Department of the Province of Havanaand Pinar Del Rio, Chief Surgeon's Office, mentioning yellow fever cases and Dr. W. C. Gorgas. When the letters were written in 1902, Kean was chiefly in Washington, D.C.but made visits to Camp G.H. Thomas, Lytle, Georgia, and elsewhere, on Army business, while his wife Louise was visiting at Edgehilland the University of Virginia. The last two folders contain Kean's correspondence to his wife in 1912-1913, on War Department, Office of the Surgeon General stationery, describing a tour of inspection in the South, a period covered in volumes 9 & 10 of his diaries.
Another large group of correspondence consists of the letters from J. Randolph Keanto and from his mother-in-law (two folders) and Louise H. Young Keanto her mother (12 folders), Louise Hurlburt Young, beginning with the marriage of Randolph and Louise in 1894. These letters describe the Army surgeon career and travels of J. Randolph Keanfrom his wife's perspective, especially their experiences in Cuba.
Another group of letters is comprised of correspondence between J. Randolph Kean and his son, Robert Hill Kean(1900 -?) during the Great War (3 folders), while Kean was serving with the American Expeditionary Forces, Headquarters, U.S. Army Ambulance Service, chiefly in Tours, France, and Robert was attending Woodberry Forest School, and 1946-1950 (10 folders). There is also a single folder of letters from Robert Keanto his father, 1917-1918, and 1947. Kean particularly describes his work with the Services of Supply in 1918 when censorship was relaxed for those serving away from the Advance Section, also mentioning his promotion to Brigadier General, Medical Corps. He also mentions the Jefferson's Day Centennial Celebration by the University of Virginia Overseas Alumni on April 12 & 13, 1919; his marriage to Cornelia B. Knox(1919 Apr 1, 22; May 2, 26); and his receipt of the Legion of Honor from the French government (Apr 13).
There are also four folders of condolence letters and telegrams to J. Randolph Keanupon the death of his first wife, Louise H. Young, 1915-1916 from friends and associates. Other folders of correspondence include one of letters from Robert Landis Hershey to Robert Hill Kean, 1924-1927; one of John Kean to J. Randolph Kean, 1942-1950; and a folder of miscellaneous Kean familycorrespondence, 1859-1950. The latter folder includes: a recommendation for R.G.H. Kean(1859); Nannie R. Keanto her brother R.G.H. Kean(1868 Oct 26); Professor John B. Minorre the "Miller Deed to the University of Virginia" (1869 Mar 12); V. Dabney(1873 May 17); letters from R.G.H. Keanto Addie Keanwhile visiting J. Randolph Keanat Ft. Sill, Indian Territoryand St. Francis Barracks, St. Augustine, Florida(1887 & 1894); a summary of R.G.H. Kean's debt (1897); newsclippings concerning the Edgehillfire in 1916 and the death of Lancelot Keanin 1931; and Louise Keanto J. Randolph Kean(1906 Oct 10).
The last group of correspondence consists of miscellaneous correspondents to Cornelia Knox Kean and Jefferson Randolph Kean alphabetically arranged. These include: Estela Agramonte; Alderman Library; Mary Beth Anderson; Randolph Anderson; John H. Andrus; David Rankin Barbee; Grace Berl; Mrs. George A. Bradford; Frank P. Brent; Honorable Jefferson B. Browne; Mary Stuart Chamberlain; Robert L. Chason; Josephine Colt; Ross Cooley; Mary Coolidge; Helen Crump; John Dalton; Annis & John [Ewell]telegram; Alfred Fanton; General Charles Fevrier; Caroline Gallup(sister of J.R. Kean); William Crawford Gorgas; Andy Hall; Mrs. H.L. Harrell; Dr. Phillip S. Hench; Lancelot Minor Kean; Mary E. Lazenby; Fitzhugh Lee; Camilla Lippincott; Major Lledge; Mary McAdie; Professor W.F. Magie; Aunt Maria Mason; Colonel Edgar W. Miller; Grace Minns; Pattie Morris; General [R.M.] O'Reilly; Papers of Thomas Jefferson, returning a letter press copy of a letter from Thomas Jefferson to Martha Jefferson Randolph(1792 June 22); James M. Phalen; William S. Potter; J. Wardwell Proctor; Randolph Family; Colonel Robert Isham Randolph; Alice Young Rich; Frank B. Rogers; A. Owen Seaman; J.F. Siler; Mary R. Slocum; Willard Springer, Jr.; Eloise A.C. Suter; Olivia Taylor; Kim Vardaman; H.A. Webster; Peggy Wells; Walter Muir Whitehill; William Holland Wilmer; and Mason Young.
Container List
- Diaries of Dr. Jefferson Randolph Kean, 1891-1921; (15 Volumes) (Box Box 1)
- Diaries of Dr. Jefferson Randolph Kean, 1921-1940; (15 Volumes) (Box Box 2)
- Diaries of Dr. Jefferson Randolph Kean, 1940-1950; (9 Volumes) (Box Box 3)
- Order Book of Dr. Jefferson Randolph Kean, including France and Boston, 1884-1924 (Box Box 3)
- Memoranda Book of R.G.H. Kean, ca. 1865-1866 (Box Box 3)
- Journal & Itineraries of Marches from Ft. Robinson to: 1) Fort Duchesne, Utah (1888); 2) Badlands, South Dakota, with Princeton Scientific Group (1890 Aug); 3) Fort Wishakie (1890 Sep), 1888-1890 (Box Box 3)
- Notes re Dr. J.R. Kean's Diaries, Volumes I-VI, n.d. (Box Box 3)
- Memoranda re The Military Surgeon, 1926-1932 (Box Box 4)
- Memoranda Books kept by Dr. J.R. Kean, ca. 1943-1949; (3 volumes) (Box Box 4)
- Temperature and Weather Records kept by Dr. J.R. Kean, including notes about the garden, ca. 1927-1949; (6 volumes) (Box Box 4)
- Robert Garlick Hill Kean to Dr. J. Randolph Kean, 1879-1887; (9 folders) (Box Box 5)
- Robert Garlick Hill Kean to Dr. J. Randolph Kean, 1888-1891 Jul; (9 folders) (Box Box 6)
- Robert Garlick Hill Kean to Dr. J. Randolph Kean, 1891 Aug-1894 Oct; (10 folders) (Box Box 7)
- Robert Garlick Hill Kean to Dr. J. Randolph Kean, 1894 Nov-1898; (6 folders) (Box Box 8)
- Mrs. R.G.H. Kean to and from Jefferson Randolph Kean, ca. 1880-1922 (Box Box 8)
- Dr. J. Randolph Kean to Louise H. Young Kean, 1898-1900 (Box Box 8)
- Dr. J. Randolph Kean to Louise H. Young Kean, 1902, 1912-1913; (3 folders) (Box Box 9)
- Dr. J. Randolph Kean to Louise Hurlburt Young, 1894-1904, n.d. (Box Box 9)
- Louise Hurlburt Young to Dr. J. Randolph Kean, 1896-1922 (Box Box 9)
- Louise H. Young Kean to Louise Hurlburt Young, 1885-1896 May; (3 folders) (Box Box 9)
- Louise H. Young Kean to Louise Hurlburt Young, 1896 Jun-1908; (9 folders) (Box Box 10)
- Dr. J. Randolph Kean to Robert H. Kean, 1917-1919; (3 folders) (Box Box 11)
- Dr. J. Randolph Kean to Robert H. Kean, 1946-1948; (6 folders) (Box Box 11)
- Dr. J. Randolph Kean to Robert H. Kean, 1949-1950; (4 folders) (Box Box 12)
- Robert H. Kean to Dr. J. Randolph Kean, 1917-1947 (Box Box 12)
- Letters to Dr. J. Randolph Kean re the death of his wife, Louise H. Young Kean, ca. 1915-1916; (3 folders) (Box Box 12)
- Telegrams to Dr. J. Randolph Kean re the death of his wife, Louise H.Young Kean, 1915 Dec (Box Box 12)
- Robert Landis Hershey to Robert Hill Kean, 1924-1927 (Box Box 13)
- John Kean to Dr. J. Randolph Kean, 1942-1950 (Box Box 13)
- Miscellaneous Kean Family Correspondence, [1859]-1950 (Box Box 13)
- Miscellaneous Correspondents to Cornelia and Dr. J. Randolph Kean, ca. 1882-1951; (4 folders) (Box Box 13)